Good morning, today's דף daf is נ"ג. nun-gimmel. We pick up on
נ"ב עמוד ב' nun-bet amud-bet about fifteen lines from the bottom, the
two dots, and we're dealing again with the case of אונאה, ona'ah,
not by an over or undercharge of an item, but of using
money that is not the full weight, that's a little bit not
because again we're talking about a time when it was—it was worth
its—its value in terms of the metal or close to it—a little
bit more than its value probably in terms of the metal. Anyway,
and what happens if the coin is a little bit lacking? So
the משנה mishnah says, the two dots here, ונותנו למעשר שני ואינו
חושש שאינו אלא נפש רעה. venoteno lema'aser sheni ve'eino choshesh she'eino ela
nefesh ra'ah. This coin which is not complete, you know, not exactly
in mint condition, you can give it for מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni,
and you don't have to worry about this because anybody who won't
accept it is only like, you know, a stingy person. It's not
the right thing to do to not accept it. Now, what exactly
that means is a significant debate, you know, in terms of what
type of coin are we talking about. There are three possibilities: a
coin that's lacking less than the amount of אונאה, ona'ah,
a coin that's lacking exactly the amount of אונאה, ona'ah, and a
coin that's lacking even more than the amount of אונאה. ona'ah. So
we're going to—that's three possibilities. And we're going to rule out the
third case because that's like—would be extreme to say you could use
that for מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, especially
if what the משנה mishnah means, we'll assume what the משנה mishnah
means is, is that you could treat it as its face value
for מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. Okay, so within that possibility, although תוספות
Tosafot raises some others, what it means is here you have something
that's face value is a סלע sela but it's lacking a tiny
little bit.
And let's—the easiest read is that if it's under the amount of
אונאה, ona'ah, so therefore you can use it as its face value
even though a storekeeper would have a right to say—אונאה ona'ah means
after you give it, can I get it back? Can I get
a refund? Any storekeeper has a right, you know, like we have
the right to refuse service, any storekeeper has the right to say,
"I'm sorry, this is not a hundred percent a full coin, I
won't accept it." But the type of person that would do that
would be a very miserly, stingy, you know, type of a person,
נפש רעה. nefesh ra'ah. So since basically normal people will accept this
at face value because it's under the amount of אונאה, ona'ah, you
can use it as face value for מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. That's—well,
I don't know, because technically it doesn't have its full value and
somebody could refuse it. But that's not such a חידוש. chiddush. The
other way of reading it is that even if it's worth the
amount of אונאה, ona'ah, even if it is one twenty-fourth lacking, you
can still use it for its face value because even though it's
technically true that somebody not only is entitled to refuse it but
is actually entitled to get, you know, the difference back, but you
know, normal people are going to use it anyway. And therefore, you
can use it as its face value for מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni.
So two different ways of reading it, there's some other possibilities but
we'll go with those. Let's take a look—if it's really like, you
know, אונאה ona'ah is something you shouldn't be doing. Right, well the
problem with that is also that when you come to ירושלים Yerushalayim
to now, you know, use it, you might not be able to
get its full value because, you know, and that's part of the—that
would be the חידוש chiddush even in the first one. Maybe I
shouldn't be allowed to do it on any coin that's not a
hundred percent complete because even though most people will accept it, I
might have a harder time using it when I get to ירושלים
Yerushalayim and therefore it might, you know, be worth a little bit
less. Let's read the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, אמר רב פפא שמע מינה,
Amar Rav Papa shema mina, we can hear from this משנה, mishnah,
האי מאן דמוקי מזוזי, Hai man de-muki mazuzei, somebody that is super
like very, you know, exacting about what type of money to accept,
like he won't accept things that are a little bit off, מקרי
נפש רעה, mikrei nefesh ra'ah, is called a, you know, stingy, a
miserly soul. Okay, והני מילי דסגי ליה, ve-hani milei desagi lei, but
that's only if the money really has, again I'm using that word,
has currency. You know, can goes—goes, meaning the money is, you know,
is accepted. So money that would normal people would accept and the
guy—the storekeeper could take it and he could use it somewhere else
and he still refuses to accept it, he's a נפש רעה. nefesh
ra'ah. Okay, but money that—that has a hard time being accepted, obviously,
you know, that you're not a נפש רעה, nefesh ra'ah, you're just
being responsible. All right. Now, so now let's try to get into
the bottom of this משנה. mishnah. מסייע ליה לחזקיה, mesayei lei le-Chizkiyahu,
this idea whether it's the
משנה—sounds mishnah like it's the משנה mishnah מסייע ליה, mesayei lei, not
this previous statement about נפש רעה, nefesh ra'ah, the משנה mishnah supports
חזקיה. Chizkiyahu. דאמר חזקיה, damar Chizkiyahu, בא לפורטה, ba le-forta, if you
come to change it, you know, change it into smaller bills, smaller
denominations, פורטה בשוויה, porta be-shavya, then you're going to change it with
its value. It's not worth the full face value, so you're going
to change it with its actual value. It's actually worth a little
bit less than a סלע. sela. בא לחללה, ba le-chalela, when you're
coming to transfer the קדושה kedusha of מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, מחללה
ביפה, mechaleila be-yafeh, you can treat it like a—like a mint coin,
you can treat it by its face value. All right, so that's
sort of the point of the משנה. mishnah. You might have to—which
by the way suggests that it is the amount of אונאה, ona'ah,
because it suggests that you won't be able to get the face
value when you come to exchange it. Okay, so even though—so the
גמרא Gemara says,
מאי קאמר, mai ka-amar, what's it saying? Meaning, either רש"י Rashi says
that the first line is obvious, if it's not worth its face
value, of course you're not going to get its face value. Or
that the two lines are somewhat contradictory. Is it worth its, you
know, I mean is it worth its its actual metal value or
is it worth its face value? Which one do you go by?
So the גמרא Gemara says, הכי קאמר, Hachi ka-amar, here's how you
have to read it. אף על פי Af al pi כשבא לפורטה
keshabo lefortah פורטה בשוה, portah beshavah,
even though it's going to be true that when you come to
spend it in a store to get change for it, you're not
going to get the full value of the coin, you're going to
get its actual metal value, right? It's a little, maybe it's 1/24th
lacking or whatever it is, people won't give you the face value,
ובללחללו מחללו ביפה. uval lechalelo mechalelo beyafeh.
Okay, but when you are coming to...
did I skip a line? אבל מכדי כשבא לפורטה בשוה כשהוא מחללו
מחללו ביפה. Aval mibe’i k’sheba lefortah b’shaveh k’shehu mechalelo mechalelo beyafeh.
But nevertheless for מעשר שני maaser sheni you're allowed to treat it
as its face value even though in the exchange מעשר שני maaser
sheni is going to lose out, right? Because you're going to go
to ירושלים Yerushalayim and you're going to spend it and most likely
people are not going to give you its face value for it.
So that's the גמרא Gemara now. The גמרא Gemara is going to
ask, is this really true that you're allowed to do this and
have מעשר שני maaser sheni lose out a little bit in the
process? You are losing out. I mean you're supposed to eat מעשר
שני maaser sheni yourself. Well, okay, but
I don't know, you could always eat whatever food you want to
eat, but food won't be eaten בקדושת מעשר שני. bikdushas maaser sheni.
Okay, so now, which is why by the way that it's because
it's a
big, it's a bigger חידוש chiddush that way. It's an easier read
to say that it's actually not כדי אונאה. kedei ona’ah. It's a
very... it's even a tinier loss and therefore most people might very
well give you the full value. But anyway that's the question about
how to read this case. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
גמרא Gemara says like this.
למימרא דסבר חזקיה, Lemimra desavar Chizkiyah, this fact that חזקיה Chizkiyah is
saying this and making it very clear that מעשר שני maaser sheni
could lose out in the process shows you that חזקיה Chizkiyah is
of the opinion דמזלזלין במעשר שני. demezalzelin bemaaser sheni. You're allowed to
treat lightly מעשר שני, maaser sheni, which means it's a pretty harsh
term, but you're allowed to do it in a way that מעשר
שני maaser sheni could actually lose out some value. You don't have
to give the full respect to מעשר שני maaser sheni to make
sure it's not losing out any value in this transaction. One minute.
והאמר חזקיה, Veha’amar Chizkiyah, but wait, there's another statement of חזקיה Chizkiyah
that seems to say the opposite. מעשר שני שאין בו שוה פרוטה.
Maaser sheni she’ein bo shaveh perutah. You're now coming to redeem your
מעשר שני maaser sheni and you've got a tiny little amount left
that's worth under a פרוטה. perutah. Now I'm trying to imagine exactly
what the scenario is. What is it? You have an olive, okay?
Olive, but a פרוטה perutah is like, I mean currently a פרוטה
perutah by the way is worth less than a penny. So you'd
have to imagine, I mean I guess you could have two grains
of wheat or
something, but anyway, it's worth less than a פרוטה. perutah. And for
some reason you don't want to just put it in your pocket
and take it to
ירושלים Yerushalayim because the olive's going to get smushed in your pocket
or something. So what are you going to do with this one
olive that's worth less than a פרוטה? perutah? Okay, so and what
we're going to see later is you might think, big deal, I'll
be מחלל mechalel it on a פרוטה. perutah. Like can't I even
be מחלל mechalel for more than its value? But actually no, because
a פרוטה perutah is considered to be like not even considered really
money, okay, it's going to be a problem to be מחלל. mechalel.
Now if that's true, because it has to have value to be
מחלל, mechalel, then you should never have the option to be
מחלל, mechalel, חזקיה Chizkiyah because you don't start with something of value.
חזקיה Chizkiyah is going to say, give us a middle position. Let's
see what חזקיה Chizkiyah says. כשבא לחללו Kesheba lechalelo when you're coming
to redeem its value, put it onto money, אומר, omer,
I'm sorry, שאין בו שוה פרוטה אומר, she’ein bo shaveh perutah omer,
you say, הוא וחומשו, hu vechumsho, it and its fifth, because you
have to add a fifth when you're coming to transfer the value,
מחולל על מעות ראשונות, mechulal al maos rishonos, they should be transferred
on this $10,000 of מעשר שני maaser sheni that I'm bringing to
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, and I've already transferred my... all my whole warehouse
of מעשר שני maaser sheni onto this $10,000. Okay,
and now this extra פרוטה perutah is also on that money. Now
the point is, what do you mean it's on that money? That
money has, has that been fully exchanged for מעשר שני, maaser sheni,
right? I just transferred $10,000 of fruit on $10,000 of money that's
now מעשר שני maaser sheni money. So how can I transfer a
half פרוטה perutah on this money? The money is filled up as
it were. So the answer is, לפי שאי אפשר לאדם לצמצם מעותיו,
lefi she’ei efshar leadam letzamtzem ma’osav, because you are not, that money
is not 100% filled, if to use that metaphor, because you, you
are not being 100% exact, right? I mean was the fruit worth
exactly $10,000? Now if you're not exact, you could be not exact
in either direction. The assumption of חזקיה Chizkiyah is you're always going
to be inexact in favor of מעשר שני. maaser sheni. You're going
to make sure that you're giving מעשר שני maaser sheni its full
value. So you estimated this fruit at, let's say you estimated it
at $10,000. You know what you're going to do? You're going to
take $10,010 and transfer the money because you just want to be
totally safe. Okay, you're going to round up, in terms of estimating
its value or determining its value. And therefore, says חזקיה, Chizkiyah, any
money that has מעשר שני maaser sheni transferred on it, there's got
to be at least a half of a פרוטה perutah left of
value of that money that does not have קדושת מעשר שני. kedushas
maaser sheni. So therefore you can transfer your half פרוטה perutah onto
that money. Okay, so now the assumption here is, it's a little
funny idea, even though this object starts as less than a פרוטה,
perutah, I'm able to do an act of transferring its value as
long as I transfer it onto some money that already has קדושת
מעשר שני. kedushas maaser sheni. If the money were totally חולין chullin
or totally neutral, right, then if I'm not transferring something that started
with a value of... A פרוטה, prutah, I can't just give it
more than that value and make that money קדושת מעשר שני. kedushas
maaser sheini. But if the money's already קדושת מעשר שני kedushas maaser
sheini because of some other מעשר שני maiser sheini that was transferred
and there's some remaining value, then I can add to it the
value of this one olive of this one half פרוטה. prutah. Okay
so it's a little unclear like what that middle stage is. Either
you shouldn't be able to do it at all or why not
just transfer from a half from a little from a half פרוטה
prutah olive to a full פרוטה prutah coin? But that's his idea,
that you can do it as long as you start with the
value some money that's already מעשר שני maaser sheini money. The relevance
for us is that he assumes that any that you're always going
to round off in favor of מעשר שני. maaser sheini. That money
that you have that had ten thousand dollars of value transferred to
it was really had really like less than that amount transferred to
it. There's really some leftover value in that money. So if you're
always going to round off in favor of מעשר שני, maaser sheini,
that's the opposite of what we're saying here because we're saying here
we're saying here that you start with a that you could have
a סלע sela that's worth less than a סלע sela and transfer
מעשר שני maaser sheini of a סלע sela onto this coin. So
that's the opposite, right? We're rounding down, we're not rounding up. We're
treating something as if the coin is if it's worth more than
it actually is. Okay. Whereas according to this idea of חזקיה, Chizkiyah,
you're always going to transfer less value to the coin than the
coin is actually worth. No regarding that particular olive it is זלזול
zilzul because you're not giving it a fresh thing. That's not זלזול,
zilzul, that's the way you have to deal with it. Yes. There's
a חומש chomesh for מעשר. maaser. Yeah, it's the חומש. chomesh. Yeah.
Okay, so with the חומש. chomesh. Okay, so this is the context.
Not really does so that is way more than the פרוטה prutah
you're worried about. Well what well okay when I said ten thousand
dollars you're right I meant I meant plus the חומש, chomesh, fine,
you're correct. Anyway let's so anyway so that's the question. The question
is that you see from this scenario that חזקיה Chizkiyah assumes you're
always going to have more value in the money than the מעשר
שני maaser sheini and that's the opposite of this argument, which is
that you can transfer something to the face value of the coin
even if the coin is worth less. So how do you deal
with that? So the גמרא Gemara says לפי שאי אפשר לאדם לצמצם
מעותיו. l'fi she-ee efshar l'adam l'tzamtzem maosov. גמרא Gemara says no, מאי
ביפה בצורה יפה. mai b'yafeh b'tzorah yafah. No so the גמרא Gemara
now completely re-explains what חזקיה Chizkiyah means and what the משנה Mishna
means and so on. You know what? You're right. You don't transfer
to the face value of the coin.
So so what value do you transfer to? The metal value of
the coin. So what does חזקיה Chizkiyah mean when he says what
was the word? בעל מחלל מחלל ביפה, Ba-al mechallel mechallel b'yafeh, right?
So what it means the way רש"י Rashi explains this is going
to be a real stretch. The way רש"י Rashi explains this is
you treat this non-full value coin like you would treat a full
value coin. We just said in this other scenario that for a
full value coin when you transfer מעשר שני maaser sheini money onto
it, you don't fill up the coin, you round you know you
round up in favor you know in favor of מעשר שני. maaser
sheini. So now you've got a coin that's not a full value
coin that's a little bit חסר, chaseir, a little lacking. Okay. So
now you're going to transfer money also don't fill it up, leave
over a little extra for מעשר שני. maaser sheini. Okay. So it
really is saying is not at all פשט. pshat. Okay. And is
completely now going against what seemed to be the משנה Mishna was
saying and it's saying that you do not treat this coin like
its face value, you have to tip in favor of מעשר שני,
maaser sheini, make sure that the coin is worth more than the
מעשר שני maaser sheini and therefore actually even when it's worth under
the face value you cannot treat it like face value. You have
to treat it as actual value. דתרי זימני לא מזלזלינן ביה. d'trei
zimni lo mezalzalinan beih.
We do not do two things to be מזלזל. mezalzel. What are
the two things? One is that you're transferring it to a coin
that's a little חסר, chaseir, that you're not transferring it you know
and of course and I'm going to say this because Charlie loves
this when we talk about מעשר שני maaser sheini that the דרשה
drasha is וצרת הכסף בידך, v'tzarta hakesef b'yadecha, כסף שיש בו צורה,
kesef she-yeish bo tzurah, it had to be minted coins and Charlie
loves it because he loves pointing out that in biblical times they
did not yet have minted money. But nevertheless that is דרבנן derabbanan
דרשה. drasha. Okay. So anyway, so you might think oh so if
this coin does not have its minted value maybe it's not even
maybe it's not respectful to use it for מעשר שני. maaser sheini.
So that's one זלזול zilzul that you're using a coin that's a
little bit lower than its minted value. But you're not going to
add onto like what is it add insult to injury and go
ahead and also pretend as if it is worth the face value.
So actually when you use it for מעשר שני maaser sheini you're
just going to use it for its metal value and not for
its face value. So the upshot of all of this is against
what the משנה Mishna clearly seems to be saying, which seems to
be telling you you can actually give this coin its full value
for מעשר שני maaser sheini don't worry it's only stingy people that
won't treat it that way. We are now actually saying not that
way. You have to tip in favor of מעשר שני, maaser sheini,
make sure that the coin is worth more than the מעשר שני
maaser sheini and therefore actually even when it's worth under the face
value you cannot treat it like face value. You have to treat
it as actual value. Okay. So that's a re-read of the משנה.
Mishna. Now we're going to focus on this whole idea of less
than a שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. גופא. Gufa. Now let's focus in
on this idea of חזקיה Chizkiyah of less than a שוה פרוטה.
shaveh prutah. אמר חזקיה, Amar Chizkiyah, says חזקיה, Chizkiyah, מעשר שני שאין
בו שוה פרוטה אומר הוא וחומשו מחולל על מעות הראשונות לפי שאי
אפשר לאדם לצמצם מעותיו. maaser sheini she-ein bo shaveh prutah omer hu
v'chumsho mechullal al maos harishonos l'fi she-ee efshar l'adam l'tzamtzem maosov. Okay.
So you say it and a fifth is transferred of this half
of a פרוטה prutah to the money I already have of מעשר
שני maaser sheini money because that money I have of מעשר שני
maaser sheini money is
not
מיתיבי, Meitvei, I'll ask you on this. התרומה והביכורים חייבין עליה
מיתה וחומש. Ha-trumah ve-ha-bikurim chayavim aleiha mitah ve-chomesh. Okay, so תרומה trumah
and ביכורים, bikurim, this is a משנה mishnah in חלה, Challah, you
are liable if a non-כהן kohen eats it, you're חייב מיתה בידי
שמים chayav mitah bi-yedei Shamayim and if you go and if you
have to add a חומש chomesh if a non-כהן kohen ate it
unintentionally, he has to pay it back plus a חומש. chomesh. Okay,
ואסור לזרים, ve-asur le-zarim, and it is forbidden to non-כהנים, kohanim, which
is pretty implicit in the first statement. רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
ask just why it had to be repeated. והן נכסי כהן, ve-hein
nichsei kohen, they are property of a כהן. kohen. A כהן kohen
can use it for example,
he can go give it to another כהן, kohen, buy a כהן's
kohen cow from it, give it to a woman, marry a woman
with it. Obviously, it still has to be treated with the קדושת
תרומה kedushat trumah from the side that's receiving it, but nevertheless, he
can use it as his money, whatever its market value is, go
ahead and transact business with it as long as the other side
treats it with the proper קדושה. kedusha. ועולין באחד ומאה, ve-olin be-echad
u-me'ah,
and if it gets mixed up with other grain, with non-חולין chullin
grain, with non-תרומה trumah grain, it only is בטל batel if there's
a hundred and one times that the amount of the תרומה. trumah.
Okay, so one unit of תרומה trumah mixed in a hundred and
one units of חולין, chullin, then it will be בטל. batel. וטעונים
רחיצת ידים, ve-te'unim rechitzat yadayim, you have to wash hands before touching
it. Your hands are considered a שני לתרומה, sheini le-trumah, right, that's
why we wash hands before bread, because standard תרומה trumah would be
out of grain, would be out of bread, and therefore כהנים kohanim
before they would eat bread, you know, most of the time they
would make their bread out of תרומה, trumah, you don't because you
have all that תרומה trumah you're going to want your bread out
of it, you're not going to want חולין chullin bread, right, you
have all that grain, so before they ate bread, they would have
to wash their hands before touching the bread because hands are a
שני sheini and a תרומה trumah can become a שלישי. shlishi. Okay,
so therefore they would wash their hands. It's all דרבנן. drabbanan. Biblically
speaking, like, you can't have just a part of your body טמא
tamei with another part
not טמא. tamei. והערב שמש, ve-ha'arev shemesh, if they were טמאים tamei'im
and they went to the מקוה, mikvah, they would only be able
to eat תרומה trumah after nightfall. You know that's the first משנה
mishnah in ברכות, Brachos, right, מאימתי קורין את שמע בערבית, Me-eimatai korin
et shema ba-arvit, you know,
משנכנסו כהנים לאכול בתרומתן mi-she-nichnasu kohanim le-echol be-trumatan or something like that,
not getting the exact words but anyway, you know, when the כהנים
kohanim come in to eat their תרומה trumah at night, so after
nightfall then they're finally able to eat their תרומה trumah even if
they went to the מקוה mikvah during the day.
הרי אלו בתרומה וביכורים, Harei elu be-trumah ve-bikurim, this is the status
that applies to תרומה trumah and ביכורים, bikurim, מה שאין כן במעשר,
ma she-ein kein be-maaser, which isn't the case by מעשר. maaser. Now
when we say that, we do not mean מעשר ראשון, Maaser Rishon,
that's obvious. מעשר ראשון Maaser Rishon has no קדושה. kedusha. What we
mean is by מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. מעשר שני Maaser Sheni does
have a קדושה. kedusha. It has to be eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
you know, it has, you transfer its value to coins. You know,
so therefore even though it has that קדושה, kedusha, it can be
eaten by non-כהנים, kohanim, obviously. You bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim and
you eat it when you're not transferring the money. It is not
your property, that
a question about, A, you don't have the full right to spend
it on everything you want. תוספות Tosafot has that discussion specifically like
the גמרא Gemara said you can't buy it for, let's say, you
can't use it to buy a shroud for a dead body, maybe
you can't use it to buy slaves, there's a question about what
you can transfer, meaning there's two issues. If you transfer the קדושה
kedusha of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni onto money, then you can only
use that money to buy food, ונתת הכסף בכל אשר תאוה נפשך
בבקר ובצאן וביין ובשכר. ve-natata ha-kessef be-chol asher te'aveh nafshekha ba-bakar u-va-tzon
u-va-yayin u-va-shekhar.
But let's say you didn't transfer the money, its value to money,
I brought these ten bushels of whatever of apples or whatever of
grain to ירושלים Yerushalayim
and I see that you have a nice cow to sell, I'm
going to give you these bushels of grain, you'll eat the grain
with קדושת מעשר שני kedushat Maaser Sheni and you'll give me the
cow, am I allowed to do that? So that's an interesting question.
תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion about what are the extent that
I can use it, but there's some things I'm not allowed to
use it for. More significantly, רש"י Rashi says this is the position
of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni is considered to be ממון גבוה, mamon gavoah, which means,
yes, it is, you have the right to eat it in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, somebody else can't come and steal it from you, you have
the solitary right to eat it, but you're still basically eating God's,
you know, food, you're not even your food. It's like the question
when a כהן kohen eats from a sacrifice, right, we sort of
say משולחן גבוה קא זכו, mi-shulchan gavoah ka-zakhu, he's eating off of
God's table. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni,
even though it's from your fruit and you bring it to ירושלים
Yerushalayim and you're the only one who has rights to it, you
know, you can give it to somebody else, but nevertheless, it's not
conceptualized as yours, it's conceptualized as God's. Okay, and that has implications,
like if I would give it to a woman and say הרי
את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li with this מעשר שני, Maaser
Sheni, I did not give her any anything that I have, you
know, anything that's considered to be my property. Okay, it's something I
have rights to eat but not my property. So that's not that's
not true by מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and ועולין באחד ומאה ve-olin
be-echad u-me'ah now, that's what we're going to focus in. מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni is בטל batel like normal things are בטל, batel, you
don't need a hundred and one to be מבטל mevatel it, washing
hands you don't have to do before it, although תוספות Tosafot says
you have to wash your hands before you eat מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni but not before you touch מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. And if
you had to go to the מקוה, mikvah, you do have to
go to the מקוה mikvah before eating מעשר שני Maaser Sheni if
you're טמא, tamei, but you don't have to wait for nightfall. So
all these things apply by תרומה trumah and ביכורים bikurim and not
by מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Why is this relevant for us? It
seems to have nothing to do with a half of a פרוטה
prutah of קדושה. kedusha. So we're going to focus... focus in on
this issue of ביטול. Bittul. So let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי משאין כן במעשר? Mai mash'ein kein
b'maaser? What does this mean that this doesn't apply by מעשר שני?
Maaser Sheni? Something does apply by מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, right? Yes,
but not by accidentally eating it. You're right. The חומרא Chumra of
תרומה Terumah is if a non-כהן Kohen accidentally ate it, he has
to give the כהן Kohen the value plus a חומש. Chomesh. מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni is a חומש Chomesh when you're intentionally redeeming its
value. Okay, so מאי משאין כן במעשר? Mai mash'ein kein b'maaser? What
does it mean with this is not the case by מעשר? Maaser?
לאו מכלל דמעשר בטל ברוב. Lav miklal d'maaser batel b'rov. מעשר Maaser
does not need a hundred and one to be בטל. Batel. מעשר
Maaser is בטל ברוב. Batel b'rov. Now, that's a funny idea. We
normally talk about like sixty, not, you know, not a simple majority.
So it's a whole complicated thing. We're actually learning this right now
in כשרות Kashrut in the ישיבה. Yeshiva. But anyway, certainly biblically speaking,
when something does not give off taste, if it's grain getting mixed
with grain and it's all mixed together, it's בטל ברוב. Batel b'rov.
All right, it might be that under some cases if it's considered
as an interesting question, you know, I'm not going to go into
that. It's going to be way too distracting. Interesting for me, but
way too distracting for all of you. Anyway, there are times where
you might need sixty. But so and sometimes the ראשונים Rishonim say
that when the גמרא Gemara says בטל ברוב, Batel b'rov, it's לאו
דווקא Lav davka רוב. Rov. But it just means you don't need
a big amount, okay? Whatever the standard amount, either רוב Rov or
maybe sixty times, which is a normal amount when we're concerned about
taste or things that might make us similar to cases of taste,
but you don't need a hundred and one. Okay, and the question
is why not by מעשר? Maaser? And this is what we're going
to focus in on. So pay attention. Where does the hundred and
one come from anyway? That's not our issue. They learned it from
a פסוק. Pasuk. I mean, it's rabbinic. They wanted to give a
big amount to show the קדושה Kedushah of תרומה. Terumah. Okay, now
why is this relevant, this issue of ביטול? Bittul? משאין כן במעשר.
Mash'ein kein b'maaser. ואי איתא דחזקיה, V'ee ita d'Chizkiyah, if חזקיה Chizkiyah
is correct that there is a way of transferring the קדושה Kedushah
even when it's less than a פרוטה, Perutah, so הוי ליה דבר
שיש לו מתירין. Havei lei davar sheyesh lo matirin. Why is מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni ever בטל? Batel? There's a way that it's something
that can be made permissible through a different way. וכל דבר שיש
לו מתירין אפילו באלף לא בטיל. V'chol davar sheyesh lo matirin afilu
b'elef lo batil. Something that has a way of being made permissible
is not בטל Batel even with a thousand. Now, this idea that
דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar sheyesh lo matirin is not בטל, Batel,
okay, the standard... let me give you an easy example. I don't
know, easy, whatever. Here's an example:
חדש Chadash before
פסח. Pesach. Right? New, the new grain before פסח. Pesach. So when
פסח... Pesach... after the second day of פסח, Pesach, it's going to
be מותר, Mutar, right? After the עומר, Omer, the day the עומר
Omer is brought. Okay, this grain gets mixed up with other grain
before פסח. Pesach. Okay, it's a week before פסח. Pesach. We're not
worried about חמץ, Chametz, okay. Gets mixed up with other grain. Is
it בטל? Batel? Can I eat it? The answer is no, because
it's going to become מותר Mutar anyway. It's going to become מותר,
Mutar, you know, in a like in a after a certain period
after some time and therefore ביטול Bittul does not work. What is
the logic that דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar sheyesh lo matirin ביטול
Bittul does not work? So the standard explanation, the one that most
likely to occur to you, the one that רש״י Rashi says is,
we're not going to let you use this concept of ביטול Bittul
to let you ingest היתר Heter when there's another way you can
eat it when it's really מותר. Mutar. Okay, if your only option
is basically throw this stuff out because it's a mixture or eat
it, that's when we'll apply ביטול. Bittul. But if you've got another
option available, just like wait a week. Okay, then wait the week
and eat it then. You know, why should you allow yourself... why
should we let you use this concept of ביטול? Bittul? There's another
explanation, which is a little more complicated, I'm not going to go
into, but anyway, that's דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar sheyesh lo matirin
is not בטל. Batel. Why didn't you use חמץ Chametz as an
example, דבר שיש לו מתירין? Davar sheyesh lo matirin? That's a good
question. So חמץ Chametz is a... there's a debate in the ראשונים
Rishonim whether חמץ Chametz is considered דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar sheyesh
lo matirin because it gets a little complicated. But on the face
of it, that's another good example. Okay, חמץ Chametz is another good
example. Okay. Another example the גמרא Gemara talks about is on יום
טוב Yom Tov if you have an egg that was laid on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, so it's נולד. Nolad. So can it be
בטל Batel on יום טוב Yom Tov itself? When you're making an
omelet, it got mixed up in other eggs. Or do we say
no, you know, one more day, it's going to be מותר Mutar
after יום טוב, Yom Tov, don't eat it on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. But ironically, because of דבר שיש לו מתירין, Davar sheyesh lo
matirin, now you're not going to have it. You're not going to
have it. So because if the issue is you might as well
just wait, some of the פוסקים Poskim say if you'd have to
throw it out, like if it would spoil by the time you'd
have to wait, then you are allowed to eat it because you
don't have that as an option. Okay. So anyway, that's a whole
interesting discussion of דבר שיש לו מתירין. Davar sheyesh lo matirin. Now,
the גמרא Gemara says so מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, now here's an
interesting thing. מעשר שני Maaser Sheni you might say it's not אסור.
Asur. It's not like it has מתירין. Matirin. מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
is מותר. Mutar. Just eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, but if
you're out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's אסור Asur to eat. So it's
considered a דבר אסור. Davar asur. And it's שיש לו מתירין Sheyesh
lo matirin because you could just redeem it. Now תוספות Tosafot says,
wait a minute, why isn't it שיש לו מתירין Sheyesh lo matirin
forget redeeming because you could do what? Go to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
תוספות Tosafot says, okay, but if you're far away from ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
that's not seen as like a feasible option. That's not seen as
a normal type of an option, right? That gets to this issue.
If דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar sheyesh lo matirin is you might
as well do the alternative, well, how reasonable is the alternative? So
you're far away from ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that's not an option. But we
shouldn't let it be בטל Batel because you could just transfer the
value and eat it. So therefore, why do we allow ביטול Bittul
to work? Why don't we just tell the guy, you've got some
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni mixed up here... Just say the מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni in this mixture is transferred to this money. Why do
we let you eat it without doing the transfer of the value?
That's a reasonable question, right? So now, what does this have to
do with חזקיה? Chizkiyah? This should be a question for anybody. Why
is מעשר שני ma'aser sheni ever בטל? batel? Just say, redeem it.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to say, you know, that's such
a good question that we're going to say the case here in
this משנה mishna that says מעשר שני ma'aser sheni is not בטל
batel is a special case, because a normal case, I mean מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni is בטל, batel, excuse me, is a special case.
Because a normal case it shouldn't be בטל batel because you could
just redeem it. So the case that it is בטל, batel, excuse
me, is a special case that it can't be redeemed. What's מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni that can't be redeemed? Oh, I have an idea.
Less than a פרוטה. perutah.
So we're going to get to תוספות. Tosfot. So because there's going
to be another sort of, you know, source that's going to explicate
that the case of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni that's בטל batel is
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni that can't be redeemed because it's less than
a פרוטה, perutah, we say, one minute, but that doesn't work with
חזקיה, Chizkiyah, because according to חזקיה, Chizkiyah, even if it's less than
a פרוטה, perutah, it can still be redeemed. And therefore, if it
could still be redeemed, it shouldn't be בטל batel because יש לו
מתירין, yeish lo matirin, because just redeem it. Okay, that's a very
complicated way to ask a question on חזקיה. Chizkiyah. Okay, let's take
a look. וכל דבר שיש לו מתירין אפילו באלף לא בטיל. V'chol
davar sheyesh lo matirin afilu b'elef lo batel. So therefore, given that
we're going to say that the case that מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
is בטל batel is less than a פרוטה, perutah, and that allows
it to be something that's אין לו מתירין, ein lo matirin, that
there's no way to redeem it, but that doesn't work for חזקיה,
Chizkiyah, for חזקיה Chizkiyah you could redeem it. So the גמרא Gemara
says וממאי דמעשר שני במעשר. umi'mai d'ma'aser sheini b'ma'aser. First the גמרא
Gemara is going to question the assumption. How do you know that
line in the משנה mishna that says מה שאין כן במעשר דבטיל
ברובא ma she'ein kein b'ma'aser d'batel b'ruba means תרומה terumah is 101
and מעשר ma'aser is בטל ברוב? batel b'rov? That there's ביטול bitol
by מעשר. ma'aser. You know, מעשר ma'aser is more lenient than תרומה.
terumah. דילמא dilma maybe it means the opposite. לא בטיל כלל. lo
batel klal. תרומה's terumah בטל batel 101 and מעשר ma'aser is not
בטל batel at all. Maybe מה שאין כן ma she'ein kein means
מעשר ma'aser is stricter. And why is it not בטל batel at
all? Because יש לו מתירין. yeish lo matirin. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says no. לא מצית אמרת הכי. lo mat'san b'hachi. That is
not an option to explain the משנה mishna that way. דלגבי תרומה
חומרי דתרומה קתני. d'legabei terumah chumrei d'terumah katani. We're talking about the
ways in which תרומה terumah is stricter, more weighty than מעשר. ma'aser.
קולי דתרומה לא קתני, kulei d'terumah lo katani, not that it's more
lenient. Okay. So if תרומה's terumah 101 as contrast to מעשר, ma'aser,
that must mean that מעשר ma'aser is בטל batel with less than
101.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, this משנה mishna is not
listing just all the stringencies of תרומה, terumah, there's some leniencies here
too.
והא קתני בנכסי כהן. v'ha katani b'nechsei kohen. It says that they
are the property of the כהן. kohen. That's a leniency that the
כהן kohen is considered to own it in a way that a
person does not own their מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. So the גמרא
Gemara says no. לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka da'atach. Nevertheless, it does
not make sense to, so you're right, the משנה mishna is not
all the stringencies of תרומה, terumah, there's some leniencies, nevertheless, it does
not make sense to say that מעשר שני ma'aser sheni is not
בטל batel because we've got another ברייתא braita that says it is.
דתניא, d'tanya, we taught בהדיא, behedya, we have another ברייתא braita that
says this point explicitly. מעשר שני בטיל ברובא. ma'aser sheni batel b'ruva.
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni is בטל ברוב. batel b'rov. Now, I gotta
tell you by the way that there is a question about what
this ברייתא braita really says because you'll notice something very strange about
the language. מעשר שני בטיל ברובא. ma'aser sheni batel b'ruva. What would
you, ברובא b'ruva is Aramaic. And בטיל batil is Aramaic. Right? So
all of a sudden
those two
key words which are saying what the גמרא Gemara wants it to
say, that מעשר שני ma'aser sheni is בטל ברוב, batel b'rov, were
stuck in, were glossed in. But from the continuation, it's nevertheless clear
that that's the assumption of the ברייתא, braita, okay? The גמרא's Gemara
not changing the meaning, it's just explicating the meaning because let's continue
to read the
ברייתא. braita. ובאיזה מעשר שני אמרו, uv'eizeh ma'aser sheni amru, what type
of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni is allowed to be בטל ברוב? batel
b'rov? Is אין לו מתירין, ein lo matirin, is only מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni that can't be redeemed. במעשר שאין בו שוה פרוטה, b'ma'aser
she'ein bo shaveh perutah, either number one, this, and this is really
what's the basis of our question, that this is saying מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni is בטל batel if it can't be redeemed. What type
of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni can't be redeemed? Two scenarios. Number one,
it's less than a
פרוטה. perutah. ו v means or, שנכנס לירושלים ויצא. shenichnas l'yerushalayim v'yatza.
It was brought into ירושלים Yerushalayim and brought out. And we're going
to discuss later why that would prevent it from being redeemed, but
for now we'll assume that that means you can no longer redeem
it. Okay. So here's a ברייתא braita that says for מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni to be בטל, batel, it cannot be able to be
redeemed, then it's יש לו מתירין, yeish lo matirin, and what מעשר
ma'aser can't be redeemed? Less than a פרוטה, perutah, plus this other
case which we'll get to. So that's a contradiction to חזקיה, Chizkiyah,
because according to חזקיה, Chizkiyah, you can redeem מעשר ma'aser of less
than a פרוטה perutah if you get this coin that's not 100
percent filled. Okay, so now let's see what חזקיה Chizkiyah does with
it. ואי איתא לדיחזקיה, v'im it l'di'chizkiyah, if what חזקיה Chizkiyah said
is correct, ליעבד ליה כדיחזקיה, le'aveid lei k'dichizkiyah, just use חזקיה's Chizkiyah
solution. Okay. ונחליה אמעי ראשונות v'nechleih amasei rishonot and go ahead and
transfer it on money that has already had מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
value transferred to it. So the גמרא Gemara says תו פריק. tu
parik. Okay, we're talking about a case... that he has not yet
done that. He has not transferred any קדושת מעשר שני Kedushas Maaser
Sheni to, he doesn't have such type of money. So the answer's,
"So do it!" Right? What gets there... Okay, ונייתי מעשר דאית ליה,
v'neisei maaser d'is lei, before we get to doing two stages, the
גמרא Gemara says I've got even a better suggestion: take some מעשר
maaser that you haven't redeemed וניצטרפינהו v'nistarpinhu and then combine them. Okay,
meaning so you've got some basically, you know, מעשר maaser that hasn't
been redeemed plus this olive that's mixed up in this vat of
olives, like this one olive that's worth half of a פרוטה. prutah.
And the question is: is it going to be בטל batel or
not? So go ahead and say, "Okay, these olives which are definitely
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni plus that one olive mixed up in that
vat there, okay, is redeemed on this money." And then nothing is
less than a פרוטה, prutah, right? Because you're doing the whole amount.
Okay, so why not do that? You solve the half a פרוטה
prutah problem. It's half a פרוטה prutah mixed up plus other מעשר
maaser and you're redeeming it all as one unit onto some money.
So the
גמרא Gemara says
no: דאורייתא ודרבנן לא מיצטרפי. De'oraisa v'Derabbanan lo mitztarfi. You don't combine
a דאורייתא De'oraisa and a דרבנן. Derabbanan. What's a דרבנן? Derabbanan? This
olive is מעשר שני? Maaser Sheni? It's just half a פרוטה, prutah,
but it's מעשר שני? Maaser Sheni? The דרבנן Derabbanan is because from
a תורה Torah perspective, once it's mixed up, it's בטל, batel, right?
Once it's mixed up, it's בטל. batel. The idea that דבר שיש
לו מתירין davar she-yesh lo matirin should prevent ביטול bittul is a
rabbinic idea. Okay, so here's the point. You've got this one olive
that's mixed up in these non-מעשר maaser olives. From a תורה Torah
perspective, it's בטל. batel. We're going to say מדרבנן miderabbanan it's not
בטל batel because of יש לו מתירין. yesh lo matirin. Okay, now
what we want to do is we sort of want to negate
the יש לו מתירין. yesh lo matirin. We're going to say, "Wait,
wait, wait, it you know, I'm sorry, wait, did I get this
right?"
Hold on. No, no. מדאורייתא mide'oraisa it's בטל. batel. Oh no, I'm
sorry. מדאורייתא mide'oraisa it's בטל. batel. Now we're we want to challenge
the idea that it's בטל batel and say it shouldn't be בטל
batel מדרבנן miderabbanan because of יש לו מתירין yesh lo matirin because
you have a way of taking this olive plus other olives and
transferring the value. Okay, and therefore it should be considered יש לו
מתירין. yesh lo matirin. And the answer is:
I'm getting a little confused here because
because it's I'm trying to figure out it's already being בטל. batel.
But the answer is is that in that case it's consider I
mean let me just see if I can sort of think this
through here. In that case, it is
it is considered to not be חייב, chayav, not be תרומה דאורייתא
Terumah De'oraisa because it's already yeah, I mean basically, how are you
supposed to combine the one olive that's mixed up with these other
things to redeem it if it's already really בטל? batel?
Because, right, the question is,
so remember the question was, the question we're dealing with is that
it got mixed up, right? And we want this is the question
about: is a half of a פרוטה prutah of מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni בטל batel when it gets mixed up? Right? That was the
issue, right? Do you remember that? Right? We had two little no,
we did, but that's what's confusing, it's like both cases combined. It
started with the idea that we said that if you have מעשר
שני, Maaser Sheni, okay, this one will be the מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni but we don't know that, all these olives. You have a
מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, we said that it's going to be בטל.
batel. Okay, now the question is: why is it בטל? batel? Because
each one of these olives is only worth a half פרוטה prutah
and therefore it can't be redeemed. And since it can't be redeemed,
therefore we're going to say אין לו מתירין ein lo matirin and
it's
בטל. batel. Since it can't it's אין לו מתירין, ein lo matirin,
there's no way to redeem
the olive in here, we don't know where it is, that's מעשר
שני. Maaser Sheni. Since there's no way to redeem it, then it's
going to be בטל. batel. Okay, so therefore we allow it to
be בטל batel with all those other olives. Now the question is:
according to חזקיה, Chizkiyahu, why is it אין לו מתירין? ein lo
matirin? Just get some money here, some we'll have to do something
else that indicates money, okay, because I'm going to draw circular money,
okay, I don't know if that indicates, we'll make a little pile
of money, okay, get some money here, okay, and just say, "This
is transferred onto that money." And if this money is already מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni money, then you could add the half פרוטה prutah
value. So the answer is we don't have that money, that money
hasn't been transferred yet. Okay, we don't have any מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni value that's been transferred. You have money, but you don't have
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni value on it. Okay, says the גמרא, Gemara,
here's what you should do: take other olives that are worth obviously
combined more than a פרוטה prutah and say, "These olives plus this,
wherever it is, you don't know where it is, plus whichever one
is here is transferred onto that money." And now you have stuff
that's worth obviously combined it's worth ten פרוטות prutos and you can
go ahead and transfer it. So the גמרא Gemara says you can't
do that. Because these olives are
have to be have to have their value transferred מדאורייתא. mide'oraisa. These
have קדושת מעשר שני מדאורייתא. kedushas Maaser Sheni mide'oraisa. The olive in
here no longer has קדושת מעשר שני מדאורייתא. kedushas Maaser Sheni mide'oraisa.
The olive in here is already בטל. batel. Our discussion is maybe
it shouldn't be בטל batel because of יש לו מתירין, yesh lo
matirin, right? That's a rabbinic issue. But from the תורה's Torah perspective,
this is already בטל. batel. So you cannot combine this and this.
This is biblically obligated in מעשר, maaser, even the one that's in
here, even if we call it
יש לו... yesh lo... The דאורייתא d'Oraisa and דרבנן d'Rabbanan is that
the olive inside that's mixed up only has a דרבנן d'Rabbanan identity.
Right. I mean, even if we say it's not בטל, batel, if
we say it is בטל, batel, it doesn't have any identity. Even
if we say it's not בטל, batel, it's only a דרבנן d'Rabbanan
identity. It's only right. So at most this has דרבנן, d'Rabbanan, so
you can't combine it. So ironically, because we're not going to let
you combine it, that's why we're now going to say it's not
בטל batel because... no, that's why we're going to say it is
בטל batel because now it's אין לו מתירין. ein lo matirin. Yes.
But מעשר שני Maaser Sheni דרבנן d'Rabbanan today anyway. All right, so
two דרבנן's? d'Rabbanan I don't know, we're not getting into that. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so דאורייתא, d'Oraisa,
דרבנן, d'Rabbanan, דהא הוי דאורייתא ודרבנן ולא מצטרפי. de-ha havei d'Oraisa v'd'Rabbanan
v'lo mitztarfi. וניתי
דמאי! venaysi demai! Ah, so don't...
so get these olives to not be, sort of like what Charlie
says, get these olives to not be classic מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni,
which is דאורייתא d'Oraisa obligated, but get these olives from stuff that
might have, you know, דמאי, demai, which is stuff you buy from
a normal farmer, an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, and maybe it's had
מעשר, Maaser, maybe it's not, it's only rabbinically obligated. So take stuff
that's only rabbinically obligated and then we could combine this דרבנן d'Rabbanan
obligation with this דרבנן d'Rabbanan obligation. So the גמרא Gemara says וניתי
דמאי? venaysi demai?
דילמא אתי לאתויי בחדא. dilma asi l'asuyei b'chada. We won't let you
do that. We won't, because if you do that, next time you'll
come to take stuff that is not דמאי demai and therefore we
won't allow it. So since even though it would work, here's the
point though, remember. If we say there's a path to transfer the
money, it's actually going to make things harder. It'll say that it
won't be בטל, batel, it's יש לו מתירין. yesh lo matirin. So
we're trying to say why it's בטל batel because there's no path
that will allow you to do it. So you know what? בדיעבד
bedi'eved some of these solutions might work. But if we're rabbinically not
going to permit you to do it, then it's אין לו מתירין
ein lo matirin and then it could be בטל. batel. So we
won't permit you to take דמאי demai and combine because we won't
because then you'll come next time, I don't know when it'll happen
next time, to take a דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. Okay, and that won't combine.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says וניתי שתי פרוטות ונחלליה עלייהו. venaysi
shtei prutos venachallei alaihu. So now the גמרא Gemara has an easier
answer, right? Which is what we should have said all along. Don't
do it at the same time, do it sequentially. Okay, so go
ahead and take two פרוטות, prutos, okay, you take two פרוטות prutos
and basically say what I'm going to do is I'm going to
take here...
I'm going to take here some olives that are worth one and
a half פרוטה. pruta. Okay, I'm going to do this in two
stages. Stage number one is, I know it's funny because I'm drawing
everything as circles, but the red is the olives and the black
is the פרוטות. prutos. These are where olives are. Yeah, it's true.
Anyway, it's too late. I already... anyway. So what I'm going to
do is I'm going to transfer it to here to two פרוטות.
prutos. So it's going to fill this up and it's going to
fill this half up. That's stage one. And now I've got the
חזקיה Chizkiya scenario. Meaning, the גמרא Gemara says the only reason why
can't you do the חזקיה, Chizkiya, the answer was, well because you
don't have... you don't have any money available that has קדושה kedusha
ready for, you know, already transferred onto it. So the answer is,
so get the money! So take the money, transfer some קדושה kedusha
of מעשר, Maaser, leave over a little bit, and transfer the rest.
There's still a way to do it according to חזקיה. Chizkiya. You
didn't have it? So get it! Do it in two stages. In
other words, create a scenario in which you can apply לפי שאי
אפשר לאדם לצמצם. lefi she-ee efshar l'adam litzamtzem. Exactly. Exactly. First transfer
some מעשר Maaser onto some money and then there'll be a little
left over and then do the חזקיה Chizkiya solution. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says וניתי שתי פרוטות ונחלל עלייהו מעשר בפרוטה ומחצה. venaysi
shtei prutos venachalal alaihu Maaser b'pruta u'mechtza. Take מעשר Maaser with a
פרוטה pruta and a half, דנחלל האי אהאי יתירה, denachalal hai a'hai
yeseira, and then you've left over half a פרוטה pruta and then
you could do this, so you should still be able to have
a path to be מחלל mechalel it according to חזקיה. Chizkiya. So
the גמרא Gemara says לא, מי סברת פרוטה ומחצה תפסה שתי פרוטות?
lo, mi savras pruta u'mechtza tafsa shtei prutos? Why do you think
a פרוטה pruta and a half would fill up two פרוטות? prutos?
No. פרוטה תפסה פרוטה. pruta tafsa pruta. The פרוטה pruta will fill
a פרוטה. pruta. וחצי פרוטה לא תפסה. v'chatzi pruta lo tafsa. And
the other one won't do it at all. Meaning, when חזקיה Chizkiya
said that you can have leftover money is if you started here
with not a פרוטה, pruta, with something bigger, you know, what's the
next one?
A פונדיון, pundyon, okay, some bigger amount. פונדיון pundyon I think it...
whatever it is. Okay, or a סלע, sela, whatever it is. You
start with a bigger coin and you transferred one and a half,
so you know, that'll work. So you transferred it here, you filled
up this amount and the rest is left and now you can
do חזקיה's Chizkiya trick. Okay, but here, when you try to do
one and a half onto this, the... right? These are separate coins,
it's not one big coin worth a lot, okay. So one פרוטה
pruta can take a פרוטה's pruta value. Now I've got left in
this thing a half פרוטה's pruta value. Now I'm stuck with a
coin that has no קדושה kedusha into it. I don't get to
look at two פרוטות prutos as one unit. I look at two
פרוטות prutos as separate coins. So one פרוטה, prutah, if this is
worth a פרוטה prutah and a half, I can transfer a פרוטה's
prutah value to this. And now I'm left with an empty coin
and a half פרוטה prutah here, well I can't do that. No,
here I do it all at once, right here, it's one big
coin worth two פרוטות, prutas, five פרוטות, prutas, ten פרוטות, prutas, and
I can transfer one and a half, I don't have to fill
up the coin. Why?
Because you can't when you're left with a half, you can't transfer
a half of a פרוטה prutah to an empty coin, right? So
when I do it at once, I transfer one and a half
here, right? I'm not transferring just a half by itself. I'm transferring
one and a half to a big coin. But when I transfer
one and a half to two separate coins, I have to look
at each coin as a separate thing. So to one coin I
was able to transfer one. But to the next coin, that's an
empty coin and I have a half of a half פרוטה's prutah
value. So we're back to חזקיהו's Chizkiyahu problem. פרוטה's Prutah the smallest
it goes. What? פרוטה's Prutah the smallest it goes, yeah. Oh, you
can't do three quarters in one coin and three quarters in the
other coin? No, because you cannot do, according to everybody agrees you
cannot do less than, you cannot start with an empty coin and
do less than a פרוטה prutah value. One whole פרוטה. prutah. Right.
Three quarters doesn't help. Exactly. So, you were able to do one,
fill up one coin, but you can't look at this as a
big two פרוטה prutah unit. It's a פרוטה prutah transferred to a
פרוטה, prutah, now you're left with a half and you can't transfer
a half to an empty coin. That was the whole reason חזקיהו
Chizkiyahu needed his solution. It's funny that all of a sudden the
thinking gets really concrete. Right. As the whole thing was abstract. Now
all of a sudden, how many coins you have, these little קדושה
kedusha containers. Right. And a half a פרוטה prutah is nothing. Right.
It can't, it doesn't stick. Exactly,
exactly. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: okay, fine, so
big deal, so don't use two פרוטות, prutas, use a bigger coin.
So the גמרא Gemara says, פרוטה
תפסה פרוטה
וחצי פרוטה לא תפסה הא דהוה דאורייתא ודרבנן דאורייתא ודרבנן לא מצטרפי.
Pruta tafsa pruta v’chatzi pruta lo tafsa ha dehavei de’oraisa v’derabanan de’oraisa
v’derabanan lo mitztarfei. And then you're left with like a half פרוטה
prutah here, and if you wanted to try to combine this half
פרוטה prutah with this half פרוטה, prutah, this half פרוטה prutah is
a דאורייתא de'oraisa obligated and this half פרוטה prutah is דרבנן derabanan
because this half פרוטה's prutah already בטל. batel. You remember that? Right?
So in, so A, here you tried to do it, you're left
over a half of a פרוטה. prutah. Don't tell me now to
combine it, I can't combine a דאורייתא de'oraisa and a דרבנן. derabanan.
So גמרא Gemara says, fine, וניתי איסר, v’nayisay issar, so
don't start with two פרוטות. prutas. Start with a bigger coin. Start
with an איסר, issar, okay, and therefore, I forget how many פרוטות
prutas that's worth, let's say two, whatever it is. And therefore, you
do one and a half to here, leave over a half, and
then do חזקיהו's Chizkiyahu solution. Basically, it's a complicated way of saying:
I don't care if you have the money or not, you can
get the money. And why don't you do חזקיהו's Chizkiyahu solution, if
חזקיהו Chizkiyahu is correct? So גמרא Gemara says,
דילמא אתי לאתויי פרוטות. dilma ati l’atuyei prutas. No. Now that we've
established that it won't work with two פרוטות prutas and it'll only
work with one bigger coin, we won't let you use a bigger
coin because you'll come to use פרוטות. prutas. So we went through
a whole complicated thing to say that if you have a half
of a פרוטה, prutah, it's אין לו מתירים ein lo matirim and
it's בטל. batel. And we said one minute, according to חזקיהו Chizkiyahu
יש לו מתירים. yesh lo matirim. You know, and we made a
complicated way of saying we're not going to let you, yes, חזקיהו
Chizkiyahu is still correct, but in this scenario, we're not going to
let you do חזקיהו's Chizkiyahu solution, because we're afraid you're going to
mess it up. Since you're going to mess up the details, we're
not going to let you do it. And because we're not going
to let you do it, we're allowing it to be בטל. batel.
They're right, because a person will say "Are you kidding me? It's
the same value." Right. Who cares if it's a two איסר issar
coin or two, right? No one will think that concretely. Correct. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: okay,
that got us out of the whole reason we discussed that, which
was to try to disprove חזקיהו, Chizkiyahu, and in the end we
sort of said, "Well, חזקיהו Chizkiyahu could be right, but we won't
let you do it." Now we're going to look at scenario number
two where it's אין לו מתירים. ein lo matirim. Scenario number two
where this thing is בטל batel because I can't redeem it is,
שנכנס לירושלים ויצא. shenichnas l’Yerushalayim v’yatza. That's scenario number two. It was
brought into ירושלים Yerushalayim and taken out, and therefore there's no way
to redeem it. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ואמאי? v’amai? So what? ולהדר ונעייליה? v’leihadeir v’nayeileih?
First of all, as תוספות Tosafot says, forget redeeming it. The first
case we could say you were far away from ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so
saying bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim is not יש לו מתירים. yesh
lo matirim. But here you just were in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and you
just left, so why is it אין לו מתירים? ein lo matirim?
Just walk back into ירושלים Yerushalayim and eat it there. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, ושנתטמא. v’shenitma. Oh, it became טמא. tamei. So
it can't be eaten anymore with קדושת מעשר שני. kedushas ma’aser sheni.
It can be redeemed. So now the גמרא Gemara says, ונפרקיה? v’niferkei?
So go back to what we were saying before, redeem it. דאמר,
D’amar, but now maybe you'd think once it was brought into ירושלים
Yerushalayim it can't be redeemed. The whole idea was to redeem it
before you got to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, okay? דאמר, D’amar, but no, now
that you said it was טמא, tamei, you can redeem it. דאמר
רבי אלעזר מנין למעשר שני שנטמא שפודים אותו אפילו בירושלים? D’amar Rabbi
Elazar minayin l’ma’aser sheni she’nitma she’podein oso afilu b’Yerushalayim? Normally you can't
redeem מעשר שני ma’aser sheni in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the whole idea to
redeem it was to allow you to bring it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
But Rabbi Elazar says if it's טמא, tamei, and you can't eat.
it, then you can redeem it in ירושלים Yerushalayim
because you redeem it to money, you use the money to buy
טהור tahor fruit, and then you are able to eat it. So
how do you know you're allowed to do this in ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
שנאמר כי לא תוכל שאתו. shenemar ki lo tuchal se'eto. You cannot
carry it, ירושלים Yerushalayim you can redeem. ואין שאת אלא אכילה. ve'ein
se'et ela achila. שאת se'et is just, in this דרשה derasha means
you can't, not you can't carry it, but you can't eat it.
שנאמר וישא משאת מאת פניו. shenemar vayisa mas'et me'et paneiv.
And he sort of gave the gifts, you know, in front of
him from יוסף Yosef and the brothers, and was talking about food
that he gave them. Okay, so therefore he says if you can't
eat it because it's טמא, tamei, you're allowed to redeem it even
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So we're back to the question. If it's not
טמא, tamei, bring it into ירושלים. Yerushalayim. If it is טמא, tamei,
then you should be able to redeem it. So why is this
אין לו מתירין? ein lo matirin? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא
בלוקח בכסף מעשר שני. ela belakuach bechesef maaser sheni. Okay, what we're
talking about is stuff that was, you used מעשר שני maaser sheni
to
buy. It's not the מעשר שני maaser sheni itself, it's stuff that
was bought with some money of מעשר שני. maaser sheni. And we're
going to assume that stuff that was bought, like it's second generation,
right? It's fruit that was bought, you transferred from the מעשר שני
maaser sheni to money, from the money to fruit. So it's fruit
that was bought with the money of מעשר שני, maaser sheni, we're
going to assume that that cannot be redeemed. You can only redeem
the first generation fruit, not the second generation. You got it? I
had all my grain, right, in, you know, in whatever in France,
I transferred it to a thousand dollars or in Tel Aviv, I
brought it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I used it to buy, you know,
apples in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, okay? And now, now I want to, I
took those apples out of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. I can't redeem it. Why can I not redeem it?
Because the assumption here is I can only redeem first generation, I
can't redeem second generation, okay? And I can't maybe bring it back
to ירושלים Yerushalayim maybe because they became טמא. tamei. All right. So
you spend all that money in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Yep. I mean, you
can have a big party and have other people come with you
and so on, you know, give it to friends. The thing is
you don't have to do it at any particular time. But you
know, think about how much that helped the tourist industry. I'm kidding.
Not kidding. You know what I mean? Everybody has an obligation to
bring all this money into ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Let's say it's 1000 and
I spent 500, I can go back home and then take that
leftover 500 and go back another time? Yeah, you don't have to
spend it all at once. Right, I have my little box at
home. Yeah, you can do that. Okay, all right. Okay, תנן. tnan.
So the גמרא Gemara says big deal. So the גמרא Gemara says
לוקח בכסף מעשר נמי ליפרקי. lakuach bechesef maaser nami lifrekei. So you
should also be able to redeem even second generation. תנן, tnan, we
taught, הלוקח בכסף מעשר שני שנטמא, halakuach bechesef maaser sheni shenitma, stuff
that's bought with מעשר שני maaser sheni money that became טמא. tamei.
Okay, so that's why you now have to redeem it because you
can't eat it, and that's what we had to say otherwise just
eat it. Okay, יפדה. yipadeh. So redeem it. So even second generation
can be redeemed if it became טמא. tamei. גמרא Gemara says no,
רבי יהודה דאמר יקבר. Rebbe Yehuda de'amar yikaver. Okay, no, but there's
another opinion that disagrees that says that second generation if it's טמא,
tamei, you can't redeem it, you have to bury it, there's no
option. אי רבי יהודה, i Rebbe Yehuda, one minute, if it's רבי
יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, מאי איריא יצא אפילו לא יצא נמי, mai irya
yatza afilu lo yatza nami, why did the ברייתא braisa say that
you took it out of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? According to him, the scenario
that you can't redeem it is if it became טמא, tamei, it's
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, okay? And now there's nothing that can be done
with it. It can't be redeemed, it can't be eaten. So then
why did you have to give the case, and that's why it's
אין לו מתירין. ein lo matirin. There's no other solution. But then
why did you have to say that it was taken out of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? That doesn't play a role. גמרא Gemara says fine,
forget that. אלא לעולם בטהור. ela le'olam betahor. We're not dealing with
רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, we're not dealing with לוקח, lakuach, we're dealing
with טהור מעשר שני, tahor maaser sheni, so what's the issue? So
why can't you redeem it? ומאי יצא? umai yatza? What did it
mean it was taken out of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? דנפל מחיצות. denafal mechitzos.
The walls of ירושלים Yerushalayim fell down. It was יצא yatza because
it didn't go anywhere, the walls just fell down around it. It's
no, there's no longer any way, if there's no walls around ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, you cannot eat the מעשר שני maaser sheni money in ירושלים
Yerushalayim without the walls. So you left ירושלים Yerushalayim not because you
left, but ירושלים Yerushalayim left you. ירושלים Yerushalayim left you, right, exactly,
exactly. Now I do have to pause for a moment and say
a fascinating תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos says, you know, the idea that
you have to ירושלים Yerushalayim have to be surrounded by walls in
order that things that need to be done in ירושלים Yerushalayim like
the eating of קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, the eating of מעשר maaser
can get done in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. תוספות Tosafos says the definition of
surrounded by walls for that purpose of מעשר maaser and קדשים קלים
kodashim kalim is a lower threshold than the definition of surrounded by
walls for שבת. Shabbos. How does he know that? Because he says
you know the famous story about how it was ערב פסח erev
Pesach was on a שבת Shabbos and they didn't know what they
could do, how could they go ahead and
שחט shacht the קרבן פסח korban Pesach on שבת. Shabbos. Secondly, how
are they going to bring their knives, right, to the carrying their
knives and whatever, and they asked הלל Hillel and he said בני
נביאים הם bnei nevi'im heim and they figured out you stick the
knife in the wool of the sheep and it carries it. So
תוספות Tosafos says I don't get it, if in order for them
to be bringing קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, the ירושלים Yerushalayim had to
be surrounded by walls. So if it was surrounded by walls, who
needed to, right, you could carry your knife, it's got an עירוב,
eruv, it's surrounded by walls. So anyway, so תוספות Tosafos says it
must be that the definition of surrounded by walls
for
מעשר שני... maaser sheni... That's the עירוב Eiruv they don't hold of.
That's the עירוב Eiruv they don't hold of. Anyway, yeah, what, really,
we hold of that עירוב Eiruv right there? Anyway, okay. So anyway,
okay. So that's the answer. So it's יצא. yatza. So the reason
it's אין לו מתירים ein lo matirim is we're going to assume
that you cannot redeem the value once there are no longer walls
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Now why is that true? Let's take a look.
The גמרא Gemara says, ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, or once it was,
excuse me, here's the point. Once it was in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I'm
sorry, here's the point. Forget redeeming. It was brought into ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Once the fruit is brought into ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the normal principle we
say is you're no longer allowed to redeem, right? The one exception
remembers we said if it became טמא, tamei, then there's no other
way to eat it. But the normal rule is once it's brought
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you cannot redeem it, even if you take it
out you have to bring it back. Okay, that's the normal thing.
Now in this case you brought it into ירושלים, Yerushalayim, boom, you
can't redeem it anymore. Now the walls fell down. So I can't
eat it in ירושלים Yerushalayim and I can't redeem it, so that's
the case of אין לו מתירים. ein lo matirim. That's what the
גמרא Gemara says. So now let's see how the גמרא Gemara challenges
this. One minute. ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, but doesn't רבא Rava say
מחיצה לאכול דאורייתא? mechitzah l'echol d'Oraisa? The הלכה halacha that you need
a wall around ירושלים Yerushalayim to eat in ירושלים Yerushalayim is a
תורה Torah הלכה. halacha. מחיצה לקלוט דרבנן. mechitzah liklot d'Rabbanan. The idea
that a wall absorbs it, meaning makes it no longer permissible to
be redeemed, דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. That idea that once it's brought to ירושלים
Yerushalayim you can't redeem it anymore, that's only rabbinic. Okay, but so
what? It's still rabbinic, I still should not be able to redeem
it. No, because now we're going to argue that the rabbis would
not have applied their law in this case.
וכי גזרו
רבנן כי איתנהו למחיצות? v'chi gazru Rabbanan ki isnehu l'mechitzot? When did
the rabbis say that you can't redeem once it was brought in
ירושלים? Yerushalayim? When the walls of ירושלים Yerushalayim are still up, when
you're still able to eat it in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. והיכא דליתנהו למחיצות, v'heicha d'leitnehu l'mechitzot, if the walls have
fallen down, לא גזרו רבנן, lo gazru Rabbanan, presumably they would let
you redeem it, right? There's no other option now. Presumably they'd allow
that case. הגמרא ha-Gemara says, לא פלוג רבנן. lo plug Rabbanan. The
rabbis wouldn't—didn't distinguish. They made a categorical rule. בין איתנהו למחיצות ובין
ליתנהו למחיצות, bein isnehu l'mechitzot u-vein leitnehu l'mechitzot, whether they're there or
not there. So now we have a good reading of this ברייתא.
Braisa. The walls fell down. Because you were in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you
can no longer redeem it, that's a rabbinic law, but we're going
to stick to that law even after the walls fell down. You
can't eat it because there's no walls and you can't redeem it
and you're stuck and it's אין לו מתירים. ein lo matirim. Okay,
let's do one more answer.
רב הונא בר יהודה אמר רב ששת, Rav Huna bar Yehuda amar
Rav Sheshet, חדא קתני. chada katani. No, no, no. This case of
less than a פרוטה perutah and going in and out
of ירושלים Yerushalayim is all one case.
מעשר שני שאין בו שווה פרוטה שנכנס לירושלים ויצא. Maaser sheini she-ein
bo shaveh perutah she-nichnas l'Yerushalayim v'yatza. Both things are true, less than
a פרוטה perutah and went in and out. Therefore, it can't be
redeemed. Therefore—so now we're back to our question: why can it not
be redeemed? Right? אמאי? Amai? Because we're going to bracket that half
of a פרוטה perutah part for a moment. אמאי ונהדריה וניכליה? Amai
v'nahadreih v'nichleih? Bring it back and eat it. וניפרקיה? v'nifrekeih? דנפול מחיצות.
d'naflu mechitzot. Same answer: the walls fell down. וניפרקיה? v'nifrekeih? So—so what,
the walls fell down, so you could—still should be able to redeem
it. דאמר רבא מחיצה לאכול דאורייתא מחיצה לקלוט דרבנן. d'amar Rava mechitzah
l'echol d'Oraisa mechitzah liklot d'Rabbanan. Because רבא Rava says that this whole
idea that you can't redeem it after brought in ירושלים Yerushalayim is
only rabbinic. So even if the walls fell
down—now that the walls fell down, the rabbis should allow you to
redeem it. וכי גזרו רבנן כי איתנהו למחיצות היכא דליתנהו למחיצות לא
גזרו רבנן. v'chi gazru Rabbanan ki isnehu l'mechitzot heicha d'leitnehu l'mechitzot lo
gazru Rabbanan. We're re-doing what we did before, right? So we should
say that if the walls really fell down, the law that you
can't redeem it is only דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. So in this case, the
rabbis should allow you to redeem it. הגמרא ha-Gemara says, לא פלוג
רבנן. lo plug Rabbanan. The rabbis didn't distinguish. So we're back to
where we started before. The scenario is when it—you didn't take it
out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the walls fell down. Because it was brought
in, it can't be redeemed, that's rabbinic but we're going to stick
to that. And because the walls fell down, you can't eat it,
so therefore it—it can't be redeemed. Now so therefore all we said
in the—so we just went through the whole thing again. But what
we just did is we helped our חזקיה Chizkiyah point because we
said this case combines with the case of it's also a half
פרוטה, perutah, both of these things are true. So now הגמרא ha-Gemara
is going to say, then why does it have to be a
half פרוטה? perutah? So הגמרא ha-Gemara says, אי הכי מאי איריא אין
בו שווה פרוטה? ei hachi mai irya ein bo shaveh perutah?
So you've now just given an explanation where it can't be redeemed,
you know, and it's not related to not having a פרוטה. perutah.
Why are you saying this plus it's not—not worth a פרוטה? perutah?
אפילו יש בו נמי, afilu yesh bo nami, even if it is
a פרוטה, perutah, you shouldn't be—shouldn't be able to redeem it now
that the walls fell down. הגמרא ha-Gemara says, לא מיבעיא קאמר, lo
mibaya ka'amar, which is totally not פשט. pshat. In this ברייתא Braisa
it means
when—when we say less than a פרוטה perutah we're saying it goes
without saying. Meaning, certainly more than a פרוטה perutah can't be redeemed,
but even less than a פרוטה perutah can't. לא מיבעיא יש בו
דקלטנהו מחיצות, lo mibaya yesh bo d'kaltnehu mechitzot, if it has a
פרוטה, perutah,
then it really was seen as like contained by the מחיצות, mechitzot,
right, because it had value. That would be a type of thing,
things worth a פרוטה perutah you would say once they went into
ירושלים Yerushalayim they're no longer allowed to be redeemed. אבל אין בו,
aval ein bo, but if it has less than a פרוטה, perutah,
it doesn't even really have value, so in that case, אימא לא
קלטנהו מחיצות. eima lo kaltnehu mechitzot. So maybe even after it was
brought in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's nothing of, it's not worth, it has
no significance. So maybe even after it was brought in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
it could be redeemed. It's not like it was, it was defined,
its status was defined by being in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. קמשמע לן kamashma
len that it doesn't matter, yes a פרוטה, prutah, no פרוטה. prutah.
So bottom line, what did we say? The two scenarios of מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni that cannot be redeemed is number one, less than
a פרוטה, prutah, which either is a proof against חזקיה Chizkiyah or
it's some or it's some way in which חזקיה Chizkiyah is not
an option because of the circumstances. And the idea that it was
brought in and out of ירושלים Yerushalayim merely means it was in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, can't be redeemed, that's a דרבנן d'rabanan law. And then
the walls fell down and now it can't be eaten in ירושלים
Yerushalayim and now you're stuck. And the last answer just said, okay,
we'll say that's also talking about the case of a half פרוטה
prutah so we get around the חזקיה Chizkiyah problem that way. Okay,
so that's the end, we've now explained why it can't be redeemed,
we will pick up tomorrow continuing to look at this issue of
redeeming מעשר שני ma'aser sheni that is worth less than a פרוטה.
prutah.